Yo, yo, yo, sup critical thinking
listeners? This is Justin Gardner, aka
Rhino Raider, and I am rolling solo
today. Joel got some conflu and is out.
Um
So, I've got my I've got my water and
I've got a whole list of awesome news
topics. It's been a couple weeks since
we've been able to do any news or write
up coverage or anything like that. So,
we have an absolute doozy today.
We have 1 2 3 4 5 at least five awesome
write-ups we need to cover.
So, I'm going to take a sip and we'll
get started.
Okay,
first one up on the list today
is of course and also for any of you
that are listening that also want to
watch I've got my because Joel isn't
here today I'm going to add a little bit
of the visual stimulus stimulation that
Joel normally provides and share my
screen for those of you that are
watching on YouTube. So, hopefully you
should be able to follow along there as
well.
All righty, so the first the first thing
we were going to cover is of course if
James Kettle ever releases anything then
we need to jump on that right away. And
he does it once again this year at Def
Con he does every single year drop some
crazy research. This year it's called
Smashing the State Machine the true
potential of web race conditions.
And this is a great read. It's actually
not that long
as opposed to or as compared to some of
his other research that he's released
and it's a really like beautiful and
simple technique to really improve upon
race conditions. So, to give you the
TLDR of it there's a couple things that
we need to take away and talk about from
on this
Excuse me, from this research.
The first one is the fact that race
conditions often take advantage of or
abuse this thing called the state
machine which is why he's he's writing
about it and why it made it into the
title. So, as the application is
processing a request it transfers
between different states. And abusing
those states is what makes the race
condition. So, he has a really great
example here of
a race condition which is not a
particularly hard to to reproduce race
condition or a particularly technically
challenging race condition. But
essentially when you're signing up for
an account there would be a post to this
is an example he has here a post to
login
and then a post to
a get to
roll. And he kind of maps out
here the different states that the
machine goes through. When you you know
you're your login state when before you
do  post to  login is
null. And then after you have logged in
you assume that because it redirects you
directly to  roll that you know
your account goes into a pending state.
That's what it looks like on the screen.
That's what the user makes the
assumption off of. And then after you
select your role it does a post to
roll and assigns you the role.
However, you can only be assigned the
role that you you know are allowed to
select from the list on the
on the  roll page. And so that's
the way that that this sort of state
machine um
flow went according to you know the
natural progression of our thought.
However, he noticed that
when you are able to
intercept the application before you hit
roll by default your account
gets assigned admin permissions.
And this is an example of the state
machine doing something a little bit
funky. And this is a this is a
multi-step race condition. You know,
there's if we just pause before
roll and then do a request
somewhere else then we have admin
permissions and that's great. But
but So, this is a multi-step. This takes
multiple requests. But the assumption
then that he explores within the rest of
the paper is that there are these sort
of sub states that happen within the
processing of a single HTTP request. And
then how can we abuse these sub states
to get us access to crazy cool
functionality?
So, that's the first thing you need to
understand this whole concept of sub
states.
Let's say you know during the
application there's a line of code that
says okay you know user's added by
default give them admin permissions or
set you know the role to zero or
something like that which is also
you know admin. And then later on in
that same code flow it says
okay now update the role to staff in the
example that they that he had here.
How do we catch it at that at that you
know at the
the timing between when we have the
admin role and the staff role is
assigned between that in order to
exploit that. And so that's kind of what
he talks about through the rest of the
paper is this concept of sub states and
how to hit those. And
due to race conditions being very tricky
with
you know distance between you to the
target server and just you know the
the sequential nature of HTTP 1.1
race conditions have been very
challenging. And in the past
James has talked about this whole
concept of a of a last last byte sync
which allows us to get really really
fast
and well-timed race conditions
in HTTP 1.1. And this
attack that is the second concept that
we want to explore during this
this sort of summary of his research is
the single packet attack and that is
sort of a way to do something similar
but a little bit better for HTTP 2.
And the reason this is possible
is because HTTP 2 is not a a protocol
that has to be
sent uh
synchronously you know or
sequentially excuse me. It can also be
it can be sent concurrently
and it can be split across multiple
TCP packets.
And so
Yeah, so the concept here is and let's
see if I can find the part of the
application the
blog here so that you can see it for
those of you that are watching along on
YouTube.
Yeah, so
he said you know this concept
essentially had was already explored
back in 2020. Actually there's another
reference to it up here
I believe.
I can't I can't find it. This is this is
the struggle with actually you know
having the screen on. Oh here it is
right here. Yeah, this is inspired by a
presentation back in 2020. And if you
look at this timeless timing attacks
presentation that he mentions in the
blog
you know this is this is just another
example of James going and finding
research that was definitely undervalued
and just reading a bunch of weird papers
and then being like oh wait I can do
something crazy with this and then
taking it. And this is what he's done
for the past years. So, it really talks
to the importance of finding sort of way
out there you know not in the mainstream
of infosec research reading it just out
of pure curiosity and then building upon
it.
So, the whole concept for the single
packet attack is
um
he he talks about essentially sending
the full body the headers if you have if
you have
body in your HTTP request sending the
body except for the last byte. Um
And then having taking advantage of
something called
Nagle's algorithm which is a sort of a
TCP optimization
that was made in order to solve
something called the small packet
problem in TCP. But essentially what
this allows you to do is build up a a
buffer of of data up to the maximum
segment side size MSS and then send that
all at once. And so what essentially
he's abusing here
is sending the last byte of all of these
HTTP requests that he wants to send in
one TCP packet. And that will
using using and abusing here Nagle's
algorithm for this. And what that will
ensure is that all of these HTTP
requests get
completed at the same time when that TCP
packet is is processed by the by the
server.
And that allows us to not only have you
know all of them syncing within sub 1
millisecond which is phenomenal
but also it allows it allows us to
delete any sort of network jitter.
Where is the mention to it? I think it's
up here.
Yeah, you can see like
normal
request will have network latency and
jitter
that you've got to
you know accommodate for. But this
single packet attack can literally get
it to sub millisecond synchronization
across these these requests which is
just amazing for race conditions.
Really great idea. And I really like
here how he also mentions
has a section of the write-up called
Rolling Your Own Implementation. And
this is this kind of breaks down the
HTTP 2 configuration that you should use
the way that you should modify an HTTP 2
library in order to be able to roll your
own implementation of the single packet
attack. And it's surprisingly simple.
Like he says here know, it can fit into
one little screen segment.
Um
and the TLDR of it is
if the request has no body, send all the
headers, but do not send the end stream
flag. Now, the end stream flag is a flag
that's attached to a HTTP/2 request
that indicates you know, something about
that request, right? And so, if you
don't add the end stream flag, it
indicates that that that that request is
not complete yet.
Um and that this server should not start
processing it.
If the request does have a body, send
all the headers and the body data except
for the final byte, sort of like a last
last byte sync attack from last year.
Um and
the reason for that is that it says you
might be tempted to send the full body
and rely on not sending the end stream,
but he's done some experimentation with
HTTP/2 servers and some of them will
just ignore the end stream, you know,
the fact that the end stream flag is not
present and just
start processing the request anyway,
which breaks the race condition. So, you
can see he's really done his research
here and it's a really simple and
beautiful algorithm and it should be he
says right here you should be able to
verify that all of the packet that all
of the requests
landed in a single packet using
Wireshark. So, it should be pretty easy
to validate that your attack is actually
working properly using this. And of
course, they've integrated all of this
stuff into Burp as well as per the usual
flow with um
with James in the in the PortSwigger
team.
Um
the other shout out that I wanted to
make here was I I bounced over to the
HTTP/2 RFC. Uh and this is actually like
a pretty manageable size RFC, right?
Like some of them are like really really
long and really really
um you know, hard to read, but this
actually seems pretty manageable in
size. So, I think
I I
I haven't done it yet, just just full
disclosure, but I think after this after
this I record this podcast, I'm going to
go through here and just read through
this because I think it could be really
helpful to know
um you know, what all of this looks like
and HTTP is such a core part of being a
solid web hacker, obviously.
Um you know, you spend so much time in
the requests
and HTTP/2 is just going to continue to
grow in popularity. So, the more and
more familiar we are with this and I'm
I'm very familiar with HTTP/1.1. Um so,
I think it might be time to take that
deep dive and learn a little bit more
about HTTP/2.
Um yeah, and then the last thing that I
wanted to highlight in this write-up
with James was
um his example here. So, he's talking
about
a vulnerability that he found. He always
goes and tries to you know, exploit this
on bug bounties to show proof of
concept, which I really appreciate. Um
and one of the ones that he found one of
the ones he mentioned here uh also I'll
I'll back up really quick and say you
you have to go and read this whole you
have to have to have to go and read this
whole paper because he
explains all of these really in-depth um
mentality and methodology
approaches
and and just the way he's thinking about
finding these race condition
vulnerabilities that is really
phenomenal. And I'm actually not going
to spoil it here so that you have to go
and read it.
Uh
but it it changed the way that I look at
race conditions and the way that I I'm
able to identify race conditions when I
don't have code. And it's it's hard to
do it even when you have code.
So, anyway, going back to GitLab,
he found a bug on GitLab and essentially
what it was was changing his email. And
he noticed that when he race conditioned
the change email endpoint, what would
happen is sometimes he would get a
an email containing the confirmation
code for a different email
at his email. Okay, so let's say for
example, he's he does a race condition
and he changes his email to
test one and then he changes to test two
really fast, right?
So, he he might get a a um
an email with the confirmation code for
test one at the test two address or vice
versa, the test one email at the test
two address. And the reason for that was
really cool and I I appreciated the way
he broke it down,
um
which was that when you changed your
email, a function was called and that
function would
get passed into it as a parameter the
email that the that the email should be
sent to, the email address that
the confirmation email should be sent
to. And that would be you know, and I
feel like this is a pretty common I feel
like this is a pretty reasonable way of
coding it, right?
Um so, you pass that in as a parameter
and then inside that function, this is
asynchronously,
it would
generate the the email body using a
templating engine, right? And that
templating engine, the variable for the
confirmation code would get
generated
via
templating, of course. So, it's pulling
it straight
and the way that it's it's configured
here is it's pulling it straight from
the database, right? So, what would
happen is you would send the first
request. Um that email would get passed
into the function, which would you know,
define the templating for
for the email and send out the email.
And then by the time that templating
engine was ready to in to create the
body of the email and insert the
confirmation
um the confirmation token that was
associated with that account, that
confirmation token will have changed
because the second request will have
already come in and generated a new
confirmation token, right? So, that
token is getting inserted into the body
of the the email and that email is being
sent to the original address, which is
being passed in via that original um
Excuse me, by that that original
parameter to the function. So, that's
how a a mismatched confirmation token
can get associated with his you know,
with a with an email
and sent to a different email. It's
really cool. Really like that bug and I
think it's also really cool. I'll I'll
see if I can find it in here. I'm so so
bad at finding things on the fly. Um
somewhere in this in this write-up.
Yeah, you can still view it on my
profile, he says. So, we can click on
this and it says it still has his this
email, which is unconfirmed that is
associated with his account. Very cool.
Um all right, so that's all I had for
James Kettle's write-up. And I'm going
to try to you know, as I go through some
of the deeper write-ups today, I'm going
to try to sort of pepper in a little bit
less technically dense content to kind
of give your brain a refresher.
Um
So, the next thing that I wanted to talk
about then is this tweet by Alex Chapman
and essentially what he's doing right
now is he is creating he's tweeting out
an automation development diary. So, as
he is building his own bug bounty
automation over time,
he's tweeting out how it's going and I
think this is really insightful for
those of you that and Alex is a top
hacker. We've had him on the podcast.
He's he's phenomenal, right? Um
So, for those of you that are a little
bit bummed like oh man, my recon's going
all weird, just know Alex Chapman has
spent over two days at this point on on
just getting the scope and stuff like
that for from all these different
programs and getting it all into
consolidated into one format in one
spot. And I'm sure there'll be lots of
other raw
lessons learned and
successes
and failures along the way. So,
definitely keep an eye out for his bug
bounty automation development diary
series on Twitter.
Okay, water time.
All righty.
Next piece of research, super lit. Once
again, Soroush coming in dropping some
fire on IIS. Um
Excuse me, I've got a little bit of of
nasal congestion as well.
Um
Yeah, so Soroush once again dropping
some crazy fire on IIS here.
This bug just this is crazy to me. This
is the cookieless duo drop IIS off
bypass in app pool privesc on asp.net
framework.
And this is a CVE from this year. So,
this is a newer technique.
Um
So, the TLDR of this is essentially in
when you're when you're using asp.net um
in in IIS,
you can send a
open parentheses S open parentheses any
text close parentheses close parentheses
or I'm sorry, with a slash in the in the
beginning as well. So, slash open
parentheses capital S open parentheses
any text close parentheses close
parentheses. This is the struggle of
doing this on on audio medium. Um and
essentially that will get processed as a
cookie um
in the .NET framework and then stripped
out of the freaking um
path, right? So, it's it's like
classically Excuse me. This is like a a
beautiful beautiful way to
circumvent any sorts of
um
IIS restricted paths, right? So, it
could be you've got
path restrictions in IIS itself. It
could be that you've got
path restrictions in you know, an Nginx
proxy that's sitting in front of IIS,
you know, whatever it is.
There are are times when you want to
wall off a specific endpoint and it's
it's very common to do that using a
reverse proxy and this just totally like
destroys all of that. And for those of
you that are following along on YouTube,
you can see right here. This this just
is crazy to me. So, let's say we've got
an endpoint
called slash web form slash protected
and
you shouldn't be able to access anything
in protected, right? So, what he does
here is slash web form slash and then
that S
parentheses X thing that I mentioned and
then slash pro t
right? So, the first couple the first
four characters of protected and then he
just inserts in there the  s
x sort of combo thing, right? And then
he says
acted at the end of that. Now, what's
going to happen is that  s x
thing is just going to get totally
deleted from the path. We can see it
down here. He he cites the code um this
remove app um
path modifier piece of code. You can see
right here that it returns um
the path with without the
the little um session cookie indicator
in there.
Um and just strips it right out, which
allows you to just perfectly bypass any
sort of path-based restrictions. Um
super awesome. Love this technique. And
then there's this other thing down here
called uh
related to application pool confusion.
And um I'm going to be perfectly honest
with you. I didn't like super fully
understand this, but from what it looks
like to me is you can use this um
cookie-less session token injection in
here
in order to get your path um or or the
code that you're running within a
specific path uh a
executed within a different context,
which is an application pool in IIS. Um
which can allow for the escalation of
privileges. Say for example, you don't
have the ability to run uh ASPX code or
whatever in a specific app pool, but you
do in another. How can you get the code
that's in that non-executable
path to run in the other application
pool and this is is possible via this um
cookie-less injection. Once again,
definitely worth a read and um
so definitely check out Soroush's blog.
Um we'll link it down below, but it's
soroush.me
um for those of you that don't don't
know it already. Um and so really cool
really cool research here. Um I'll
mention as well that at the beginning of
this blog he says uh for a deeper dive
into security issues stemming from the
use of cookie-less sessions, consider
these references. So, um he lists uh
uh three other places where you can go
and read
about it and I absolutely read this one
right here uh the isec.pl blog, which is
um excellent as well and this guy uh
Paveo, I believe is how that's
pronounced. Um he talks about um using
this for XSS when a a path is being
resolved from a a uh squiggly path,
right? A um a tilde path um to a
uh to a an actual path, an arbitrary
path.
Um and so for those of you following
along, you can see right here that he's
able to inject into that because that
session token is is an important part of
what should be associated with that path
and use that to get XSS. Once again, a
cool XSS technique for any of those that
are into automation uh XSS automation,
this could definitely be something
really cool to uh do mass scanning for
if you can find this um reflected in
into the um into the body of the
request, then that it would be really
cool. Um or to the body of the response,
that would be really cool.
Um
the one thing that I wanted to highlight
from this, which uh here it is right
here
is that um it's not only
open parentheses s open parentheses any
text close parentheses close parentheses
that works, but also
you can um sub that s for an a or an f.
The a is an anonymous ID and the f is a
form authentication token. Now, being
able to specify some of this stuff in
the URL is also just kind of weird um
and I feel I could definitely be used
for session fixation or um if you could
get sort of like a uh client-side path
traversal of sorts like you could inject
your own session token into it, right?
If you get a client-side path traversal,
you could inject your own session into
that request and then take the data
that's in that request and associate it
with your own account rather than with
the victim's account. Um which I think
has a lot of potential there.
Um and then yeah, uh so this is also
just helpful for bypassing uh
like WAFs or anything that might be they
might be catching on. Maybe they see
Soroush's blog and they say, "Okay, all
right, we got to block, you know, any of
this cookie-less stuff." And they block
just the s, but then you've also got a
and f you can use as well. So, keep that
in mind.
Um okay. Uh
that's all I had for Soroush's stuff.
Definitely go check out the blog. Um I
will link it down in in the description
as always. Uh we the description might
be a little long this time around, so we
might have to host it somewhere else,
but we'll figure that out.
Okay. Um unfortunately, we're going
straight into another highly technical
piece right now, so bear with me um
and we'll we'll
we'll hang in there. This is a really
cool blog, so I think you'll like it.
Okay.
Um next one is Ophion Security released
a write-up um customer account takeover
in Shopify stores. Um this is Rojan. Um
amazing bug as always. Shopify uh
There's just so much cool stuff, so many
so many cool pieces of functionality to
play around with on Shopify. Um
so uh it's always cool to see them as a
target.
Um all right. So, the way let's see what
what what did I want to highlight here?
Um let me look at my notes really
quickly. Yeah, okay. So,
I We won't go through every single step
of this of this write-up, but I did want
to to um
mention that this specific bug takes
advantage of a couple um sort of quirks,
okay? So, the first one is this concept
of an unverified email address being
associated with your account, okay? Um
and
I I imagine on the back end
for any of you blue blue teamers out
there or devs
there's a couple ways to implement this.
You could put the unverified email as
the actual email for the account and
then add a flag like is email verified
true false somewhere else in the user
object, right? Or you could put the
email in its own unverified email
attribute of the user object and um then
move it to the verified email object
whenever you do anything.
Um the latter is way more secure and the
former unfortunately is what we see
here, which I think causes a massive
vulnerability.
So, um what happens is when you sign up
for a shop account, you can um
you can change your email address or you
can specify an email address and uh
they will send a uh a confirmation email
to that email address, but for the time
being your email is still, you know,
that email.
Um and so this is weird. This is weird
um and we always want to whenever you
have an unverified email that sort of
looks like this. This is specifically um
interesting when there's only one email
associated with your account. So, this
is not like a change email sort of
feature. This is when you've signed up
for an account and only email they have
associated with you is this unverified
email, right?
Cuz then, you know, there's a better
chance that email is actually the
primary email associated with your
account. Um
and so uh
essentially what they do here is they
take this unverified email account and
they abuse the Shop Pay OAuth workflow
to log into uh a different log into a
store, okay?
So, I have this one line highlighted
right here that I really I really want
you to to dial in on. Even though a
store may not have the sign in with Shop
uh feature, I guess, fully enabled uh
and displayed in their store, it is
still possible to access the Shop Pay
OAuth directly via this endpoint, okay?
So, what they've done here is they've
shown mastery, they've shown in-depth
knowledge of the product because they
are familiar with this concept of there
is a sign in with Shop feature that can
be enabled and dis- disabled and even
when it's disabled, it's still there.
It's just not in the UI, right? Um this
is incredibly important for those of you
that are looking to develop this sort of
um spidey sense or this sort of
understanding of how to find these more
complex vulns. Any features that you can
turn on or off or that are accessible
part of the time, but not accessible the
other parts of the time, you have to
validate that because just because it's
not in the UI or just because it's not a
part of the normal flow, doesn't mean
you can't force navigate to it and then,
you know, insert yourself in the middle
of this sort of, you know, crazy flow
that that they've they've, you know,
configured here. And so that's exactly
what Rojan and the Ophion Security team
do here. Um
they hit they take their unverified
email um shop account and they use that
to sign in with Shop into a into a
Shopify store.
Um and at the end of the day, I think it
it's not as simple as just hitting that
endpoint. I think they also have to um
hit some endpoints to get the cookies
that they need and this also shows
further mastery of the of the
application. They know which cookies
need to be swapped for what and what
cookies are providing authentication in
the context of the Shopify store, um
which will allow them to uh gain access
to, you know, a fully validated account.
So, this is this is very important and
it goes it goes to the concept of
um understanding
you know,
anytime you look at a HTTP request,
you're just going to see a block of
cookies because of tracking, because of
all this and that and the other thing,
but it's very important to use something
like maybe request minimizer, even just
do this manually, removing all of the
fluff and getting down to what is
actually useful in in the application.
Figure out what is
what is resulting in authentication,
what is affecting the application
directly. And once you've narrowed that
down, you have a much greater chance of
finding vulnerabilities in those
components because there isn't so much
fluff around. Okay.
So,
that's what they've done here and that's
what results in the
or the account takeover for them.
Um
Man, that had to be a crazy bounty
because Shopify I think has I want to
say they have 200k crits max and that is
a arbitrary account takeover. So,
congrats to Rojan and the
the Offense Security team.
Already.
Uh next up, well, hold on. Let me Let me
get some water. I got to take water
between every every
topic.
Okay, next one is um
uh a tool released by Monke, uh a great
hacker and Hack One ambassador.
Um
Uh this is called short name guesser.
This is uh
We talked about this something similar
to this a couple weeks ago, but
essentially uh with IIS, there is a way
for you to specify short names and get a
true or false Windows short names. So, I
want to say it's the first six
characters
um that you can enumerate and the last
three characters of any given file in a
in a directory. Um so, but oftentimes
files are longer than six characters.
So,
Excuse me. You've got to
um you've got to figure out what the
rest of that name is. Um and I guess
Monke decided that this is a a perfect
um
use for GPT-3 and some of the AI
capabilities that we've been um
playing with lately uh thanks to OpenAI.
Um and I I couldn't agree more. I think
um essentially, if you if you know how
LLMs work, they're actually just looking
to develop the next token, right? The
next the next token in line and that's
how they they simulate all of this
wonderful knowledge and comprehension
that we've all been amazed by for the
past, you know, 6 to 8 months.
Um And so, what he did here is he he uh
developed just a a very short piece of
code. You can see here it's like 35
lines
um to utilize uh
ChatGPT or the OpenAI um
API to get a list of potential file
names
uh associated with a a given short name.
I think this is a great tool and I will
be using this the next time I'm doing uh
IIS short name brute forcing.
All right. I'm going to have to take a
big sip of water before this one.
Sam Curry has released something, y'all.
Um
For those of you that are not familiar
with Sam Curry's work, essentially every
couple months Sam and team, uh whoever
it tends to be that that time around,
releases some giant write-up that breaks
the whole internet and destroys a whole
industry normally.
And it's a excellent read and I think
it's really unique content um because
not many people not any other people
that I know of are out here um
addressing sort of industry-wide issues
like Sam. Um
And just kind of going after
you know, I I I I like to I'd like to
talk it up, but it's really Sam just
being like, you know, what would be the
coolest [__] I could hack? And then
going and hacking that. And I just I
love that about Sam.
Um and then he does these write-ups
which bless him for doing these
write-ups. They're they're so long and
they're so detailed and they really
um highlight the attacker mentality as
they go through this. So, um this is
also a mandatory read. Um the James
Kettle read earlier was absolutely
mandatory read. Um this is also a
mandatory read.
So, go read it. It's uh Sam Curry's uh
most recent write-up on points.com.
It's entitled Leaking Secrets in
Unlimited Miles, Hacking the Largest
Airline and Hotel Rewards Platform.
As you may have imagined, uh this is Sam
hacking points.com, which is a uh
provider of points for all of these
different vendors. Um he has a For those
of you watching, you can see here
um the list of vendors that he has uh
but some of the top names include Delta,
Emirates, uh Marriott, um a I IHG, uh so
many different companies utilize
points.com for their rewards programs.
Um and he does a high-level overview in
the beginning, which we're going to
skip, of course, because here at
Critical Thinking, we do low-level
overviews. We talk about the technical
details, the juicy the juicy technical
details, and we get hyped about that
[__] So, that's what we're doing.
Um essentially, what I've done is I've
broken down
um each of the sections of the rest of
this write-up and I've got some key
takeaways from all of the various
sections and I'm going to provide a
short summary. But like I said, you're
missing out on a ton of juicy data
um and hacking mentality and just vibing
if you don't go and read this. Um so,
uh that's my I I've said my piece now.
Okay, so first section is how does it
all work? Um this is kind of when he's
he's discovering how this whole
points.com thing works. He's using
Wayback Machine to uh read documentation
and understand the details behind it.
Um and one thing that I wanted to
highlight here is he he gets to this
console.points.com,
which allowed public registration, signs
up for an account, and he says, um I
just want to take a quote out. The next
thing we did was to examine the
JavaScript that powered the dashboard.
We discovered that the website
console.points.com appeared to be
utilized by points.com employees for
executing administrative actions
concerning customer accounts, rewards
programs, and managing components of the
website itself. Anytime you see
something like this, I've I've done this
a couple times, where you have public
sign up to an acc- a a portal that is
management for um all these different um
tenants that you'd be hacking, uh that's
gold. Go in there, read the JavaScript
files, figure out what it looks like to
have those requests recreated in the
background. I've personally made six
figures in bounties from
this exact scenario as well.
Um so, that's a big takeaway there. I
was also impressed um for those of you
watching, you can see the graph here.
For those of you not watching,
um essentially, he has a graph where
he's uh
outlined the way that the API the
rewards API does authentication and
unfortunately, it's a a MAC-based
authentication, which uh I'm not going
to lie. Like if if I was in Sam's shoes,
I would have totally ignored this
because I freaking hate MAC-based
authentication. Um essentially, how it
works is you've got a key and you've got
your message and every single message
that you send, every single freaking
request, needs to be um
run through this MAC algorithm and a a
message authentication code generated
and that code included with the message
um to ensure that that message hasn't
been tampered with and was sent from
someone that has the key um in order to
send that. So, um that would be a pain
in the butt, but that didn't scare Sam
at all um and they were able to do some
really cool stuff um not only despite of
it, but abusing that. So, props to them
for that.
Next section is called Exploring the uh
United Airlines point management
website. So, they take they move away
from points.com after they've learned a
lot about points how the points API
works and they go to specifically
mileageplus.com uh
bymiles.mileageplus.com,
which is a
uh United product um which is infamously
out of scope uh in the United program.
RIP. Um
And essentially, what they do here is
they go through the registration process
and sort of figure out what's going on.
Um and then they do something that which
we talk about all the time on Critical
Thinking, which is they pay the freaking
money to send miles to somebody else,
right? We always say,
you know, bite the bullet, pay your in
in the in the picture that he's got
right here, I just noticed he's
has $6,584
worth of miles he's sending somebody. I
don't know that he actually sent that
much, but if he did, that's that's
ridiculous.
Um
But he bites the bullet and he sends
some miles, pays the money, and sends
some miles to somebody else, right? So,
you know, it's Ian or Shubs Happy Day or
whoever he's hacking with this time.
They get some miles from Sam, but also
what Sam gets in return in the response
of that um
HTTP request that sends the miles is the
person's points.com user off token, the
membership authorization token. Um
Which is a big a big L for points.com
and the mileage plus United team. Um and
essentially, what that allows you to do
is by entering a person's first name,
last name, and mileage uh
a mileage plus number, which is their,
you know, account ID, um essentially,
you would get back their off token from
that request and you could use that off
token to log into their account, send
the miles back to yourself,
um and get a bunch access to a bunch of
PII. Huge huge vulnerability.
Um
great great technique um in finding that
out. So, takeaway there. Pay the money.
Just pay the freaking money and uh and
you'll find lots of ones like that. If
you see a place where you should where
you could pay money and it's like a
reasonable amount of money, you should
get really excited to pay that money.
Like that is potentially
some of the best money you'll have ever
paid, you know? Like you're going to get
some serious ROI on that. So, um that's
what we always say.
Woo, halfway through a Sam Sam Curry
blog post, you got to take another sip
of water.
Okay.
Um
So, let's talk about the next section,
escalating the issue to affect other
rewards programs. Um so, at this point,
what's happening is Sam is trying to
figure out how exactly uh the points.com
uh API is being integrated with all
these other different providers. They
did that with United, and he's trying to
do that with other
um providers as well.
And he highlights uh in the post this
HTTP request right here, which um for
those of you not watching, uh it's
there's an HTTP request with a path, and
then in the body, it has two parameters,
uh MVP payload and LPID. LPID is a UUID,
um and MV payload is an empty um
object, an empty JSON object. So, what
he does here is very interesting. He
appends a pound symbol to the end of
that LPID parameter. The reason he's
doing that is he is looking for
uh
secondary context vulnerabilities. This
is sort of a term I feel like this term
is actually coined by Sam himself. Um uh
but, this is sort of Sam's bread and
butter. I've found multiple bugs with
Sam where he exploits secondary context
bugs, and he's just a master at it. And
essentially, what's happening is he is
assuming that this ID is getting taken
and put into the points.com API in the
back end.
Um that we were talking about earlier
with the MAC authentication scheme and
that sort of thing. Um and he's trying
to validate that by putting a hashtag in
there, a pound sign. And what that will
do is that will in the uh in the URL, it
will create a hash fragment and truncate
the rest of the um the data that comes
after that uh that
uh I I UUID. And you can see from the
response he gets a 400 uh bad request
back, which um tells him that he can't
process it can't process type text/html
instead of application/json. This is a
great indicator that there is some sort
of secondary context vulnerability
that's going on.
Then, Sam uh proceeds to do all the
tricks in the book. He's adding slashes,
he's path traversing, he's using the the
uh query parameter, the question mark to
truncate and add additional query
parameters.
Um he's doing all sorts of stuff.
And essentially, what he does is he uses
a path traversal sequence to back all
the way up um to the document root, I
believe, and specify
um maybe it's not the document root,
maybe it's one above the document root,
but you can specify call call tip. You
can find the document root. This is
actually a tip that Sam taught me by
traversing past the the document root,
and then you'll note that you'll get a
400 bad request on that. Um so, really
really helpful technique there that I've
used several times. So, for example, if
the back end request is
api get user  user
ID, and that ID is where you're
injecting, if instead of the ID you put
, now
you've gone back to the root . If
you do one more ,
you'll get a 400. That will allow you to
identify the document root.
Um
So, uh what we've got going on here is
he traverses back, and he hits a
endpoint called v1
searchorders.
Um and then it says missing query
parameter needed. So, then he starts
fuzzing for query parameters in the get
using the um
what he assumed would be the get when he
specifies the path via the LPID.
Um but, unfortunately, nothing was
working there, and he then decides to
fuzz the MV payload section. Um I'm
going to start saying they instead of he
cuz I know that this is a team working
on this. So, they decide to fuzz the MV
payload section uh of that their
original request, right? That we
mentioned in the beginning, the one that
had an empty object, and it turns out
you're able to provide um post
parameters there.
Um and they provided the Q parameter,
and then it dumped back a grand total of
22 million records um back to them. Um
leaking
uh points transactions across all of the
providers. It was a god token that was
being used. Um
just magnificent magnificent
vulnerability. Um key takeaways there,
learn how to do secondary context
hacking. I've also got up on the screen
here the wonderful presentation,
legendary presentation by Sam, Attacking
Secondary Context in Web Applications. I
will link it in the description. Uh this
is also mandatory reading if you haven't
already. If you have, I would also
recommend going back and rereading it
because um if you're not finding these
vulnerabilities on a fairly regular
basis, you probably should be um cuz I
am, and Sam is. Uh so, uh definitely
check this out. Um And and if you want
another really cool example of this,
which is almost identical to this
vulnerability, Sam and I in 2020 found
uh a vulnerability on Starbucks, which
does almost the exact same thing. You
can see, for those of you watching, that
um we traversed back here and hit a
searchv1accounts
function, which dumps all of the
Starbucks accounts um that were that
were uh
in the database. It was like 99 million
records or something ridiculous like
that. Um
So,
definitely, yeah, nearly 100 million
records. Um so, definitely, these
vulnerabilities are all over the place,
and you should definitely know how to
exploit them.
Okay. Um let's see what else we've got.
Um the next little section that I wanted
to talk about was uh this uh this is
still within the Sam Curry blog post.
Um is leaking credentials for the Virgin
rewards program. Um so, this is still
within that blog post. Essentially, what
he happens here is he's kind of going
around to all the different um
uh
sort of
providers for that that are using
points.com. Um and he's trying to figure
out, you know, hey, is there any quirks
in the implementation here
that we can exploit to attack points.com
or attack their rewards program. And um
this is this is another And we we we see
a very large variety of techniques,
right? That that have happened already.
We've we've seen We've seen, you know,
the exploitation of uh
we'll just understanding JavaScript, uh
understand reading the documentation
through Wayback. Um We've seen secondary
context vulnerabilities.
Um and right now, in this one, we're
seeing uh a content discovery
vulnerability. So, this is when Sam is
just running or Sam and team, they're
running um
uh just content discovery tools like
Fuff. Um and they hit they they get a
lucky hit on login1.php, and that
login1.php leaks the MAC uh key and MAC
ID that we mentioned before that was
used for uh
authentication into the rewards API.
Now, if you see this, um normally, you
might not know what this is used for,
but Sam and the team have developed a
mastery of these this product. They've
read everything they can get their eyes
on, you know, they've they've they've
sorted through minified JS files. They
understand what's happening here. So,
when they see that MAC ID and that MAC
key, they know exactly what to do with
that. So, they were able to use that key
to authenticate into the API as the
Virgin rewards program.
Um and they were able to dump all of the
orders, all of the transactions that
have happened, um which includes it
looks like
actually plain text credit card
information.
And over looks like 2 million instances
of that. So, that's real bad.
Nice work, Sam and team. Um
the next the next one that we wanted to
uh talk about was uh this section right
here, authorization bypass uh
on widgets.unitedmileageplus.com.
And this is uh once again, another
technique um
that varies from the other one. So,
we're not just looking for IDORs, we're
not just looking for XSS, we're not just
looking for secondary context bugs.
We're looking for all of it.
Um and it requires a a large knowledge
base of different techniques in order to
be able to fully exploit some of this
stuff. So, it's really impressive to see
what Sam does, and it's also a good
lesson to us to stay to stay mentally
flexible
uh on what kind of vulnerabilities we're
looking for and how we're looking for
them.
Um so, this next one that we're talking
about here is uh this So, we're back to
widgets.unitedmileageplus.com
or United Mileage Plus programs. Um and
essentially, what they're doing here is
they're using Gau to um enumerate the
the subdomains and the different pages,
login pages that there were um to log
into this uh
widgets.unitedmileageplus.com.
And they're they're identifying that
sometimes there is a page where you can
log in with just your Mileage Plus
number, your last name, and your first
name. Sometimes it requires a username
and password. Sometimes it requires, you
know, um a security question or uh let's
see what else. Yeah, answer your
security question. There was a bunch of
variety there. And in that variety, you
know, they were noting that that um the
responses
to those were still returning a token
that looked roughly the same, right? So,
I'm just reading a quote here.
Um
Uh we found that the token returned from
each of the different authorization
methods were identical in format to each
other. So, once again, showing
application mastery, understanding what
that token looks like, un- first knowing
that that token is important, and
understanding what it looks like, um
allowed them to understand that, hey,
maybe I can take the token from the less
challenging authentication method, the
first name, last name, and Mileage Plus
number, um and use that token in the
other sections of the application where
a more challenging um authentication
method was supposed to be necessary.
Um and that's exactly what they did, and
they were able to bypass off and get
access to uh PII disclosure, um
transferring miles, essentially
arbitrary access to their Mileage Plus
account um through that that one login
that gave them an access token via first
name, last name, and Mileage Plus
number. Really cool technique. That's a
business logic error and token swapping,
right? Business logic error identifying
that there's that there shouldn't be a
way to authenticate with that
information.
And then token swapping knowing that
they can take that off token, put it
somewhere else, and access valuable
information. Really really great. Um
really great vulnerability there. Now,
the finale, they say
they say that that they still uh let's
see if I can find the
uh
So, one of the things that I really
appreciate about Sam and and the team
here uh as they're writing this up is
that mm So, he has a section named
looking for something more critical,
right? Like the bugs that he hasn't
found that he's found already just not
critical enough, you know? Like we got
to go max criticality. I mean and they
they don't give up until they achieve
it, which is really cool.
Um and they do achieve it uh every time,
so way to go, team. Or at least every
time that we're privy to, you know,
maybe there are times when they've
they've quit out uh a little early, but
um we get to see the highlights reel, so
that's really cool.
Um so, they go back to hunting on
points.com and then finally they pop it.
And how do they pop it? Is it some crazy
some crazy technical exploit that just
kind of blows your mind and path
traversal nonsense? No.
It is the fact that the JWT token
associated with the session for the uh
console website
was the word secret. All lowercase. Um
now,
this is um
This is kind of crazy to see, to be
honest. Um this sort of vulnerability
I've only found once, um but Ian Carroll
has released a vulnerability or a a tool
called Cookie Monster to exploit this
vulnerability. And essentially what it
does is it allows you to try to brute
force um and check defaults for session
configurations in
in various types of applications. I
think this is a great vuln because um
once you exploit this vulnerability, if
you have the secret key to uh you know,
JWT token, you can do whatever the heck
you want cuz you can sign the the only
thing they're using for authentication,
right?
So, in this scenario, I suppose they
they were looking at the the session
token a little bit more um in depth, and
they identified the fact that um I guess
they ran it through Cookie Monster
running a brute force against it. And in
a few sec, yeah, after a few seconds, we
had a response. It popped that the
secret that the that the um
uh secret for this JWT token was secret.
Um and so, this is a a reminder to me
and to you and to every other reader
that we need to be on the lookout for
these sort of weak cryptography
implementation vulnerabilities here
um cuz they are all over the place. And
man, they dropped some awesome
screenshots um in here of like literally
just being able to arbitrarily select a
program, you know, uh a rewards program
and just assign uh points to them. And
man, you could just literally you could
just walk around the whole world, you
know, doing whatever you wanted with
this pretty much because you just have
unlimited access to all of these points.
So,
really cool. Awesome that they got
access to that and really cool
techniques along the way as well. So,
props to Sam and the team. Um
Nice bug.
All right, water time.
We're moving along. We are. We're moving
along.
Okay. Um so, like I promised, in between
uh technical piece, we'll have a sort of
less technically dense segment. Um this
time around uh another another tweet
from uh Alex Chapman saying, "I'm in
desperate need of a platform feature,
browser plugin, or something else that
can easily show a bug bounty program's
direct competitors who also run
programs."
Um so, many bugs from one company are
directly applicable to others in the
same industry  niche. And then
Rezo comes along and says, "Dude, this
would be a sick product. Um what if
there were a way to like tag specific
functionality as well uh on specific bug
bounty programs? For example, you could
um identify a bug bounty program and tag
that, 'Hey, this has got a
a PDF generator in it.'
Or something like that where there's
specific technologies in place. This
one's using Flask.
Right? Cuz like from the last scenario,
we could go back and check the JWT um
token implementation. Um
And and so, uh he Rezo tagged me in it
and said, "Hey, shout it out on the pod.
Maybe someone will make it." And um
we've had that happen before. We shouted
out this uh this concept for a CVSS
advisor where you which I've got up on
the screen now. Uh you can find it at
cvsadvisor.com where you can just sort
of select what um you know, different uh
what what your CVSS configuration is,
and it will give you tips and um what
sort of configurations need to change
for you to bump your bug to the next
severity. Shout out to them again.
Appreciate them building that and also
uh this is my go-to CVSS tool now, so um
definitely keep that in mind. But also,
if any of you guys are looking into
uh are feeling programmy or um want to
try to decide a way or figure out a way
to tag
um various bug bounty programs
anonymously, obviously, cuz we've got
private programs, um with specific uh
features or
functionality, I think this is something
that would be widely used by hackers.
So, cool idea there.
All righty.
Let me stretch. Last uh last write-up
that we're going to cover for today.
This is a uh zero-click ATO with the
sandwich attack. This is um recently
released uh by Lupin and Holmes. Uh this
is a
uh man, look how beautiful this website.
It's just absolutely beautiful website,
l and h.tech. Um this is uh by Ronnie
Carta, uh also known as Lupin on
Twitter. Um and
yeah, essentially I think they're going
to be producing bug bounty content, and
this is a great place to start. This
write-up is on um this concept called
the sandwich attack, which abuses uh
version 1 UUIDs or UID version 1.
Okay, so um for those of you that aren't
familiar with UUIDs, UUIDs are
For those of you that aren't familiar
with UUIDs, thank your lucky stars
because they're becoming more and more
common all over the place, and they're a
pain in the ass. Um But essentially,
they're uh an alternative for numeric
IDs that should be associated with an
object. So, user ID equals 1, instead of
that, you've got user ID equals F887AA6,
you know, blahdy blahdy blah, right? Um
and so, these are very long strings
randomly generated normally, but not in
this case.
Um they contain five different sort of
segments. Um
and the
uh the segment that you should look to
for uh
the version number is the third segment.
So, um for those of you that are
have the following along on YouTube
right now, you can see right here the
the first character of the third segment
of the UID is a 1 in this scenario. Uh
normally, it's going to be a 4. If it's
a 4, that UID was randomly generated,
and you have very little chance of being
able to uh iterate across those uh UUIDs
or enumerate them. Now,
if
you know, you got really lucky or or you
found a a piece of technology that uses
UIDV1, that third segment, the first
character will be a 1. And what that
tells us is that this is not a randomly
generated UID. This is a UID that is
predictable. Um and is highly correlated
with a timestamp. Um so, uh Lupin and
the Lupin and Holmes team here do a
really great job in this write-up of
describing how uh this concept called
the sandwich attack. Uh in the in the
scenario they define, there's a password
reset endpoint. That password reset uses
UIDV1
reset tokens in order to access um to
reset the password. So, the attack would
be
Excuse me, the attack would be um you
reset your own account. That's the
first, you know, first layer of bread.
You reset the victim's account. That's
the meat. And then you reset the uh your
account again. And that's that's the top
layer of bread, right? So, you have two
reference UUIDs.
Um V1 IDs. Uh those are the two pieces
of bread. Um and those will tell you the
range of time uh uh
cuz because UUIDs correlate UIDV1
correlates directly to timestamps. Um
the range of time you need to brute
force for the middle ID, right? So, then
you use a tool to enumerate uh all of
the possible UUIDs in that range, and
then you um try those UUIDs in order to
gain access to the victim's account
um by the password reset functionality.
Great attack. I found something similar
to this before. Um and uh one of the
things I will say is we can actually
utilize this in conjunction with uh a
race condition-ish sort of thing um that
we mentioned, you know, earlier in the
in the the pod uh with James Kettle, to
make sure that these sandwiches, you
know, that this is a very thin sandwich,
right? That you can that your first
request, the second request, and third
request are all in a very small time
period because as he mentions here, um
these are in millisecond timestamps. Um
right? So, for every second that these
are off, you have 1,000 possibilities uh
for
what could, you know, that you're going
to have to brute force. So, you want to
try to get these as tight as possible.
Um and you should be able to get an
arbitrary account takeover in these sort
of situations.
All right. Um I will also note that uh
in in conjunction with this write-up
that we will be putting in the in the
description below, there's also this
awesome video uh that Lupin put out on
the their YouTube channel
walking through the actual details and
he does a lot better job of explaining
it than I did. So, definitely check that
out. Also, if you just like looking at
things with your eyes,
this is a beautifully produced
video. So, very high production quality
here. Shout out to them for that. That
takes a lot of work. I'm realizing that
more and more as I as I sort of
go deeper and deeper into the content
creation realm.
So,
great worth work Lupin and Holmes team
there.
Man, that's such a cool name. I love
that. All right. So, that's it for
today. That's all I've got.
Definitely thank you for listening to
this episode. Hopefully Joel will be
back and kicking next week so we can do
a a duo episode as usual.
If you guys wouldn't mind heading over
to ctvb.show
and dropping a subscribe on our
newsletter, we'd really appreciate that.
We're trying to grow that within the
next couple of months. Also,
for those of you that have heard me talk
about my real estate investments on the
podcast before, I I have a big
accomplishment. I'm done with the reno
that I've been working on for the past 6
to 8 months. So, super hyped about that.
Should be able to drop more time into
the pod and into bug bounty hunting
which you guys will hopefully see lots
of.
So, with that, have a great week and
thanks for listening. Bye.